<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Plants My Love</title>
	<atom:link href="https://plantsmylove.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://plantsmylove.com/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 07:04:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.0</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/cropped-Logo-Fav-1-32x32.webp</url>
	<title>Plants My Love</title>
	<link>https://plantsmylove.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How to Start a Vegetable and Herb Container Garden</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/start-vegetable-container-garden/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 07:04:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Growing Herbs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Spices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Vegetables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Your Own Food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organic Fertilizers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Irrigation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=635</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi, friends in this video you will find a framework for starting a vegetables and herbs terrace or backyard container garden. Using this framework will allow you to get a...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/start-vegetable-container-garden/">How to Start a Vegetable and Herb Container Garden</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi, friends in this video you will find a framework for starting a vegetables and herbs terrace or backyard container garden. Using this framework will allow you to get a huge harvest from your newly set-up container garden. This guide is beginner-friendly and will cover each step in detail. </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/start-vegetable-container-garden/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/dq9YrpP_Lcs/hqdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=0s">0:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=35s">0:35</a> Climate </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=177s">2:57</a> Pest and Animals </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=255s">4:15</a> Plant Selection </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=331s">5:31</a> Ahmedabad Climate</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=378s">6:18</a> Plants I will be Growing</li><li> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=410s">6:50</a> Best Gardening Season In India</li><li> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=451s">7:31</a> Seeds &amp; Seedlings </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=572s">9:32</a> Container Size </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=642s">10:42</a> Container Garden Layout </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=715s">11:55</a> Prevent Water Seepage </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=762s">12:42</a> Potting Soil and Additives </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=889s">14:49</a> Mulching </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dq9YrpP_Lcs&amp;t=975s">16:15</a> Irrigation </li></ul>



<h4>▼ Useful @ Websites▼ </h4>



<p><a href="https://www.accuweather.com/">https://www.accuweather.com/</a> </p>



<h4>▼Buy @ Seeds▼ </h4>



<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3nomUm0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://amzn.to/3nomUm0</a></p>



<h4>▼Watch @ Related Videos▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/install-drip-irrigation-system/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How To Install A Drip Irrigation System</a></li><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How To Make DIY Spray Bottle</a></li><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How To Make Bone Meal at Home</a></li><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/how-to-make-homemade-compost/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How To Make Homemade Compost</a></li><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/how-to-prevent-water-seepage-in-your-terrace-garden/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How To Prevent Water Seepage in Your Terrace Garden</a></li></ul>



<p>At first, you need to know about the things which you can not fully control. Like the climate, the pests, and animals at your place. We will first start with the climate.</p>



<h4>1 General Idea of Earth&#8217;s Climate</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-2 wp-block-gallery-1 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img width="1365" height="768" data-id="655"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Climate.webp" alt="General Idea of Earth's Climate" class="wp-image-655"/><figcaption>General Idea of Earth&#8217;s Climate</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Understanding how the earth&#8217;s climate changes depending upon the location will allow you to select the right plants for your vegetable container garden. </p>



<h5>Equatorial </h5>



<p>Generally speaking the climate at your place depends upon your location from the equator. If you are located near the equator then you will have an equatorial climate. Which does not vary throughout the year. You will have a lot of rainfall and warm temperatures around 25-30 °C. The most common example of this climate is the Amazon Rainforest. You can grow many vegetables and herbs in this climate throughout the year, but cool-season plants will not grow.</p>



<h5>Tropical</h5>



<p>As we move away from the equator we enter the tropical region. In this region, we see an annual seasonal variation in the climate causing winters and summers. Apart from this, the winters are very mild and the summers are not very hot. You will also see a lot of rainfall throughout the year. An example of a country having this climate can be Thailand. Just like the equatorial climate in the tropics, you can grow a lot of vegetables and herbs but cool-season plants will not grow.</p>



<h5>Sub-Tropical</h5>



<p>Now once we move further away from the equator we reach the subtropics. This region has got a diverse set of climate but generally speaking this region host almost all of the world&#8217;s hot deserts including the largest Sahara desert. The climate in this region is hot &amp; dry and winters are very mild. In peak summer it can be very challenging to grow vegetables and herbs. But in the winters you can grow summer season vegetables. But you will not be able to grow cool-season plants because the winters are very short and not that cold.</p>



<h5>Temperate</h5>



<p>Lastly, on going further away from the equator we reach the temperate region. In this region, the winters are very harsh and the summers are mild. In the summers you can grow plants that like the heat and in the early winters you can grow cool-season vegetables. However, once the temperature goes below freezing.  You can not grow plants outside as the frost will kill most of the plants.</p>



<h4>2 Find The Climate at Your Place</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-4 wp-block-gallery-3 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="656"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Accuweather.webp" alt="Accuweather" class="wp-image-656"/><figcaption>Accuweather</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Apart from the distance from the equator, several other factors can affect the climate at your place.  So to know exactly how the climate changes throughout the year for your place. You can check the website <a href="https://www.accuweather.com/">https://www.accuweather.com/</a></p>



<p>Just type the name of your city and then click on the monthly tab. This will show you the historical average min and max temperatures for the entire year. This will give you a good idea of the climate at your particular place. And how it changes throughout the year.</p>



<h5>Ahmedabad Climate</h5>



<figure class="wp-container-6 wp-block-gallery-5 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="665"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Monsoon.webp" alt="Monsoon" class="wp-image-665"/><figcaption>Monsoon</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>We are situated in the subtropical region. Soroudended by hot deserts. The Arabian desert in the far west and the Thar Desert in the north. The summers in Ahmedabad are very harsh. The average maximum temperature lies at around 43 °C. During the peak, summer temperatures reach as high as 47  °C. It is almost impossible to grow plants without shade cloth on my terrace garden. Because we are situated in the Indian subcontinent we have a very unique monsoon climate. </p>



<p>Every year from 15th June to 30th September we receive a lot of rainfall due to the South West Monsoon. Which brings the moisture-laden clouds from the Indian ocean up to the Arabian Sea and Bay of Bengal. But apart from this wet phase, we receive negligible rains in the remaining part of the year. This cause the air and soil to become very dry when summers peak. </p>



<p>The Winters are very mild as good as the summer in a temperate climate. So we can grow warm-season vegetables during the monsoon season and in the winters. But is difficult to grow cool-season vegetables. In the summers you will need to use shade cloth and misters to grow vegetables which I have not tried yet.</p>



<h5>Best Food Gardening Season In India</h5>



<p>If you are reading this article from India then the best time to start a vegetable and herbs garden is during the monsoon season. However, you will need to spray neem oil once a week to prevent insect attacks.</p>



<h4>3 Identify the Pests and Animals in Your Area</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-8 wp-block-gallery-7 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="657"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Pest-and-Animals.webp" alt="Pest and Animals" class="wp-image-657"/><figcaption>Pest and Animals</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Once you have got a general idea about your climate. The next thing which you cannot control is the pest and animals present at your place. These animals and pests will freeload on your hard-earned crop. So planning for them beforehand will be useful. Check with your neighbors who have vegetable and herb gardens to know the exact nature of pests and animals causing problems in your area. Once you have identified them you can try adding enclosures around your garden. To prevent them from being raided by the animals. If that is not possible you can grow plants that the animals and pests do not like. You can also use organic pesticides like neem oil to deter them from munching on your crop.</p>



<h5>Main Pest in our Area</h5>



<p>In our place, the main pest is the monkey. During harvest time they will come sneakily into the garden. And then raid the plants as if we had grown all the plants just for them. They are quite smart and I have tried different ways to protect my harvest. But over time they figure out how to bypass the protection. The only way to protect your crop from these greedy monkeys is to garden in a metal cage. However, this year I will be using a different technique. </p>



<h4>4 Select the Correct Plants </h4>



<p>Now, depending on your climate, pest, and animals at your place, you can decide on the plants you wish to start growing in your food garden. If you can not invest a lot of time and effort. I would suggest that you start by growing green leafy vegetables and herbs. These are generally easier to grow and care for compared to fruiting crops. Once you get good results with this you can then slowly expand to growing fruiting crops. </p>



<h5>Plants I Will Be Growing</h5>



<p>This year I will be growing crops that monkeys do not like to eat. Like chili, bottle gourd, cucumber, greens like amaranth, and herbs like mint, basil, and lemongrass also crop having tubers like ginger, potato, sweet potato, etc.</p>



<h4>5 Buy Good Quality Seeds &amp; Raising Seedlings </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-10 wp-block-gallery-9 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="664"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Seeds-and-Seedlings.webp" alt="Seeds and Seedlings" class="wp-image-664"/><figcaption>Seeds and Seedlings</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>If you are just starting I would suggest you go for buying mature plants from a nursery than starting plants from seeds. Some plants can be easily started from seeds. But most vegetable plants require a lot of time and care to get mature plants. For example, starting chili from seed will take you 2 months to get the mature plant which can then be transplanted into a bigger container. Apart from time, you will also need to take proper care of watering the tiny seedlings. It is like taking care of a baby. But if you have the time and inclination then it can be very rewarding. Seeing the tiny seeds develop into huge mature plants. I personally always start plants from seeds. </p>



<p>If you are going to purchase seeds make sure you get good quality seeds. The seed packet should have the packaging date mentioned on it. Because seeds older than a year, stored at room temperature have a poor germination rate. If you are from India you can get good quality seeds at an economical rate from Aero Seeds. They create a seed packet from an assortment of different vegetables and herbs. The number of seeds per plant type is limited but is good enough for one growing season. They sell online through Flipkart and Amazon over here <a href="https://amzn.to/3nomUm0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://amzn.to/3nomUm0</a></p>



<h4> 6 Size Your Containers Correctly  </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-12 wp-block-gallery-11 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="663"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Container-Size.webp" alt="Container Size" class="wp-image-663"/><figcaption>Container Size</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>While selecting the plants you need to keep in mind the size of the containers required. Large vines like bottle gourd and cucumber require around 18-20 inch wide containers. If grown in smaller containers they will grow but will not produce yield to their full potential. </p>



<p>Greens and herbs can be grown in much smaller containers. You can grow multiple varieties of greens in around  8-10 inch containers.   </p>



<h4>7 Plan Your Container Garden Layout </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-14 wp-block-gallery-13 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="662"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Container-Garden-Layout.webp" alt="Container Garden Layout" class="wp-image-662"/><figcaption>Container Garden Layout</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>To decide on the placement of the containers. You need to know the direction of the sun and the movement of shadows. Depending on the temperature and intensity of the sun. You can place the containers where your growing area receives the maximum sunshine. If you have higher temperatures you can use the shadows to your benefit like how I have done.</p>



<p>I have placed my grow bags in two-row. The first row faces the east so it receives the full morning sunshine. During the evening when it gets hot it gets shaded by the wall behind it. The second row is placed right in the middle of the terrace so it gets full sun all through the day. In this row, I will be growing the larger gourd family plants that can tolerate the heat.</p>



<h4>8 Prevent Water Seepage </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-16 wp-block-gallery-15 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="661"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Prevent-Water-Seepage.webp" alt="Prevent Water Seepage" class="wp-image-661"/><figcaption>Prevent Water Seepage</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>If you are growing plants on your terrace. You need to ensure that water does not get collected beneath your containers. There should be enough air circulation so that any moisture between your terrace floor and containers dries out quickly. This is important to prevent damage to your building because of water seepage. You can do this by installing your containers on a raised metal stand that is available on the market. In my terrace garden, I have used things that were lying around in my house. To<a href="https://plantsmylove.com/how-to-prevent-water-seepage-in-your-terrace-garden/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> create a DIY stand </a>for my container terrace garden. I have used bricks or tiles placed on granite stones to raise the containers. I have also used an old thick PVC pipe and the curvature of my terrace edge to support the tiles and bricks. </p>



<h4>9 Create the Perfect Potting Soil and Organic Fertilizer</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-18 wp-block-gallery-17 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="660"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Potting-Soil-and-Additives.webp" alt="Potting Soil and Additives" class="wp-image-660"/><figcaption>Potting Soil and Organic Fertilizer</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Good potting soil should be light, airy, rich in nutrients, and drain freely. You can purchase store-bought potting soil which can be soil-less and made from cocopeat, perlite, and added organic fertilizers. I like to be self-sufficient which saves me money and at the same time helps the environment by reducing waste. So I prepare my potting soil on my own using <a href="https://plantsmylove.com/how-to-make-homemade-compost/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">homemade vegetable compost</a>, normal garden soil, and <a href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">homemade bone meal</a>. Once the plant starts producing flowers and fruits you will need to fertilize them weekly.</p>



<h4>10 Mulching Your Soil </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-20 wp-block-gallery-19 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="659"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Mulching.webp" alt="Mulching" class="wp-image-659"/><figcaption>Mulching Your Soil </figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Mulching is a must if you are growing in containers even with raised bed garden mulching helps. There are several benefits of mulching. Mulching helps in retaining soil moisture thus preventing frequent watering. It also keeps the weed in check in addition to reducing the soil temperature by blocking the sunlight from heating the soil. If you are in a windy area then mulching will also prevent soil erosion due to strong breeze. You can create mulch from any organic material that is slow to decompose you can also use plastic as mulch. I have used the leaves of my coconut tree as mulch.</p>



<h4>11 Irrigating Your Garden</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-22 wp-block-gallery-21 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="658"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Irrigation.webp" alt="Irrigation" class="wp-image-658"/><figcaption>Irrigating Your Garden</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Once you have done all of this the only important ingredient left to get a bountiful harvest is water. You can water your containers manually but make sure to use a spray bottle or a watering can. If you pour water directly on the soil the force of the water stream will cause compaction and erosion. The fine spray from a spray bottle will elevate this problem. You can purchase a spray bottle from the market or you can make one yourself using a <a href="https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pet soda bottle</a>.  </p>



<p>If you are planning to create a large container or backyard garden I would suggest you invest in a <a href="https://plantsmylove.com/install-drip-irrigation-system/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">drip irrigation system</a>. From my own experience, I can say this reduces the gardening effort by several times. You can also add an electric valve to the system which will automate the entire process of watering. So you can go on a vacation without worrying about your plants.</p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this detailed framework for starting a vegetable container garden. Hopefully using this guide you will produce a ton of harvest. If you liked this post you will also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe </a>to our youtube channel to get notified as soon as we release a new video. Thanks for reading friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/start-vegetable-container-garden/">How to Start a Vegetable and Herb Container Garden</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Propagate Pothos / Money Plant / Devil&#8217;s Ivy</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/propagate-money-plant/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 12:24:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Growing from Layering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing House Plants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Plants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Propagation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi friends in this video I will show you how I propagate Pothos from layering. We will discuss the benefits of propagating by layering vs cutting water propagation. As always...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/propagate-money-plant/">How to Propagate Pothos / Money Plant / Devil&#8217;s Ivy</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi friends in this video I will show you how I propagate Pothos from layering. We will discuss the benefits of propagating by layering vs cutting water propagation. As always I will share with you step-by-step details.  Pothos or Money Plant is very easy to propagate. It can grow roots by simply placing them in water. But in this article, I will show you how to propagate Money Plant using layering. </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/propagate-money-plant/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/4GBfNZ67aDA/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=13s">0:13</a> Money Plant from Cutting Water Propagation </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=26s">0:26</a> Pothos Propagated Using Different Method </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=60s">1:00</a> Benefits of Propagating Devils Ivy Layering vs Cutting </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=117s">1:57</a> How to Propagate Money Plant Using Layering </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=131s">2:11</a> Find a Long Pothos Vine </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=154s">2:34</a> Use an Inert Growing Medium Perlite </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=163s">2:43</a> Benefits of Using Perlite Growing Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=213s">3:33</a> Keep 2-3 Nodes Inside the Growing Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=247s">4:07</a> Choose How Long The New Money Plant You Need </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=275s">4:35</a> Prepare Money Plant Vine for Layering </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=298s">4:58</a> Use a Stone to Anchor it in Place </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=318s">5:18</a> Bury The Vine In the Growing Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=331s">5:31</a> Keep the Pot Moist </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4GBfNZ67aDA&amp;t=357s">5:57</a> Subscribe to Watch the Growth Update</li></ul>



<h4>Money Plant from Cutting Water Propagation</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-24 wp-block-gallery-23 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="630"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Money-Plant-from-Cutting-Water-Propagation.webp" alt="Money Plant from Cutting Water Propagation" class="wp-image-630"/><figcaption>Money Plant from Cutting Water Propagation</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>This is my money plant which I propagated using the normal water cutting propagation. This is around a 2-month-old plant. But compared to the money plant which I propagated using layering just a month ago this is very small. Even the root system is tiny.</p>



<h4>Pothos Propagated Using Layering</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-26 wp-block-gallery-25 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="629"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Pothos-Propagated-Using-Layering.webp" alt="Pothos Propagated Using Layering" class="wp-image-629"/><figcaption>Pothos Propagated Using Layering</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>This is a month-old Pothos plant that developed this vigorous root system in just 20 days in the rooting medium. You can see how huge this is compared to the one which was propagated using water cutting.</p>



<h4>Benefits of Propagating Devils Ivy Layering vs Cutting </h4>



<p>There are several benefits of cloning Money Plant using layering </p>



<ul><li>The rooting time is less compared to cutting propagation.</li><li>You can get a large plant cloned.</li><li>It can be done in a climate that is not suitable for cutting propagation like hot and dry weather.</li></ul>



<h4>How to Propagate Money Plant Using Layering </h4>



<p>So now let&#8217;s look step by step at how you can get your <span style="color: rgb(13, 13, 13); font-family: Roboto, Noto, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; font-weight: 400;">Devil&#8217;s Ivy</span> cloned using layering.</p>



<h4>1. Find a Long Pothos Vine </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-28 wp-block-gallery-27 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="628"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Find-a-Long-Pothos-Vine.webp" alt="Find a Long Pothos Vine" class="wp-image-628"/><figcaption>Find a Long Pothos Vine</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>This is my Pothos plant the first step is to find a long vine that you can easily bend and place inside a pot. I will use the same vine using which I had propagated using layering previously. </p>



<h4>2. Use an Inert Growing Medium Perlite </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-30 wp-block-gallery-29 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="627"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Use-an-Inert-Growing-Medium-Perlite.webp" alt="Use an Inert Growing Medium Perlite" class="wp-image-627"/><figcaption>Use an Inert Growing Medium Perlite</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The second step is to prepare the rooting medium.  You need to use an inert growing medium like perlite. This prevents any fungal and bacterial issues while rooting the plant. Apart from that perlite also has an excellent water-to-air ratio. Which allows the root enough oxygen while keeping it moist at the same time. Also, it is impossible to overwater perlite if the drainage of the container is proper. Perlite being very light does not hinder root growth.</p>



<h4>3. Keep 2-3 Nodes Inside the Growing Medium </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-32 wp-block-gallery-31 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="626"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Keep-2-3-Nodes-Inside-the-Growing-Medium.webp" alt="Keep 2 3 Nodes Inside the Growing Medium" class="wp-image-626"/><figcaption>Keep 2 3 Nodes Inside the Growing Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Now you need to make sure that the vine which you will be layering should have at least 2-3 Nodes buried in perlite. The node region on the stem is where the leaves emerge. Root growth also happens in this region. So by placing 2-3 nodes in the rooting medium you are doubling or tripling the chance of root development.   </p>



<h4>4. Choose How Long The New Money Plant You Need </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-34 wp-block-gallery-33 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="625"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Choose-How-Long-The-New-Money-Plant-You-Need.webp" alt="Choose How Long The New Money Plant You Need" class="wp-image-625"/><figcaption>Choose How Long The New Money Plant You Need</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Now decide on the length of your newly cloned money plant will be. The stem that will be coming out from the planter will be your new plant. </p>



<h4>5. Prepare Money Plant Vine for Layering </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-36 wp-block-gallery-35 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="624"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Prepare-Money-Plant-Vine-for-Layering.webp" alt="Prepare Money Plant Vine for Layering" class="wp-image-624"/><figcaption>Prepare Money Plant Vine for Layering</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Using a pair of scissors cut the leaves from the part of the stem which will be buried inside the perlite. After that bend the stem inside the pot so that it is placed in the middle.</p>



<h4>Use a Stone to Anchor it in Place </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-38 wp-block-gallery-37 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="623"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Use-a-Stone-to-Anchor-The-Vine.webp" alt="Use a Stone to Anchor The Vine" class="wp-image-623"/><figcaption>Use a Stone to Anchor The Vine</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The stone anchors the vine and makes sure that it does not come out of the planter. The stone apart from providing support to the vine. Also, ensure the node region is in good contact with the perlite.</p>



<h4>Bury The Vine In the Growing Medium </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-40 wp-block-gallery-39 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="622"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Bury-The-Vine-In-the-Growing-Medium.webp" alt="Bury The Vine In the Growing Medium" class="wp-image-622"/><figcaption>Bury The Vine In the Growing Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Now add the remaining perlite to cover the entire vine. Make sure all the node region is well inside the perlite.  </p>



<h4>Keep the Pot Moist </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-42 wp-block-gallery-41 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="621"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Keep-the-Pot-Moist.webp" alt="Keep the Pot Moist" class="wp-image-621"/><figcaption>Keep the Pot Moist</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The last thing you need to do is make sure that the perlite does not dry out. Since I have a drip irrigation system installed in my garden I will add a dripper to this planter. You can simply water it daily. As we have used perlite there will be no problem with overwatering. </p>



<p>I hope friends you liked this detailed guide on propagating Money Plant using layering. Hopefully using this guide you will multiply your Pothos plant by several times. I will be posting a plant growth after 15 -20 days so make sure to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe </a>to our youtube channel to get notified as soon as we release the video. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/propagate-money-plant/">How to Propagate Pothos / Money Plant / Devil&#8217;s Ivy</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Propagate Chili Pepper by Air Layering</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/air-layering-chili/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Growing from Layering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Spices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Your Own Food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Propagation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=604</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi friends in this video we will learn how to clone your chili pepper plant using air layering. Air layering is a vegetative propagation method similar to cutting. But unlike...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/air-layering-chili/">How to Propagate Chili Pepper by Air Layering</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi friends in this video we will learn how to clone your chili pepper plant using air layering. Air layering is a vegetative propagation method similar to cutting. But unlike growing by cutting the plant is separate from the mother plant after root development. There is also the benefit that you do not need to care about the weather condition for it to start rooting. As the plant will get an ample supply of nutrients and water from the mother plant while it develops its own root system. </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/air-layering-chili/"><img src="//i.ytimg.com/vi/Z1j16JwODww/hqdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=0s">00:00</a><span style="color: initial;"> Intro </span></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=95s">1:35</a><span style="color: initial;"> Things Required </span></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=136s">2:16</a><span style="color: initial;"> Prepare Branch for Air Layering </span></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=187s">3:07</a><span style="color: initial;"> Prepare Plastic Bag </span></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=282s">4:42</a><span style="color: initial;"> Fill Plastic Bag with Growing Medium </span></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=347s">5:47</a><span style="color: initial;"> Seal PlasticBag using Thread </span></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z1j16JwODww&amp;t=398s">6:38</a><span style="color: initial;"> Repeat the Steps</span></li></ul>



<h4>1. Things Required</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-44 wp-block-gallery-43 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="605"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Things-Required-2.webp" alt="Things Required" class="wp-image-605"/><figcaption>Things Required</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>You will need the following things:-</p>



<ul><li>An Inert Growing Medium like Perlite, Coco Peat, Peat Moss.</li><li>Rooting Hormone (Optional)</li><li>String</li><li>Plastic Sheet</li><li>Stapler</li><li>Scissor</li></ul>



<h4>2. <span style="color: initial;">Prepare Branch for Air Layering </span></h4>



<figure class="wp-container-46 wp-block-gallery-45 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="606"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Prepare-Branch-for-Air-Layering.webp" alt="Prepare Branch for Air Layering" class="wp-image-606"/><figcaption>Prepare Branch for Air Layering</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>To prepare the stem find a node region from where a new branch is coming out. Cut the leaves and branches near the node region. This will create the space for adding the plastic bag. Now apply the rooting hormone all around the node region you can do this using a brush also.</p>



<h4>3. <span style="color: initial;">Prepare Plastic Bag </span> </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-48 wp-block-gallery-47 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="607"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Prepare-Plastic-Bag.webp" alt="Prepare Plastic Bag" class="wp-image-607"/><figcaption>Prepare Plastic Bag</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Cut a sheet of plastic that is long enough to cover the node region. The width of this plastic sheet should be good enough to carry the rooting medium. Now place this plastic sheet on the prepared branch. Using staples fold it in the shape of a cylinder to cover the complete branch node region. Using a string seal the bottom end of this cylinder.   </p>



<h4>4. <span style="color: initial;">Fill Plastic Bag with Growing Medium</span></h4>



<figure class="wp-container-50 wp-block-gallery-49 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="608"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Fill-Plastic-Bag-with-Growing-Medium.webp" alt="Fill Plastic Bag with Growing Medium" class="wp-image-608"/><figcaption>Fill Plastic Bag with Growing Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Make sure the medium is moist and then fill it up in the created plastic bag. I have used a small spoon so that it is easier to fill. Tap the medium so that there is no air gap in the node region. </p>



<h4><span style="color: initial;">5. Seal Plastic Bag using Thread </span></h4>



<figure class="wp-container-52 wp-block-gallery-51 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="609"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Seal-Plastic-Bag-using-Thread.webp" alt="Seal Plastic Bag using Thread" class="wp-image-609"/><figcaption>Seal Plastic Bag using Thread</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Once completely filled seal the plastic packet from the top using a string. This will ensure that the perlite will remain moist consistently. And that&#8217;s it now you just have to wait for a month. After one month you should see the root development. As we have used transparent plastic it will be easier for us to know when the root has developed well enough to sustain the cutting.</p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this step-by-step guide on propagating chili pepper plants using air layering. Hope using this guide you will be able to easily clone and multiply your chili plants in your garden. Don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. I will be posting the chili layering growth update after a month so make sure to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe </a>to our youtube channel to get notified as soon as we release the video. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/air-layering-chili/">How to Propagate Chili Pepper by Air Layering</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Install A Drip Irrigation System</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/install-drip-irrigation-system/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DIY Projects]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Irrigation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=579</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi friends in this video learn how to plan and set up a gravity-fed drip irrigation system for your garden. In this step-by-step guide, you will learn how to plan,...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/install-drip-irrigation-system/">How to Install A Drip Irrigation System</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi friends in this video learn how to plan and set up a gravity-fed drip irrigation system for your garden. In this step-by-step guide, you will learn how to plan, design, and build your drip irrigation system for your garden.</p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/install-drip-irrigation-system/"><img src="//i.ytimg.com/vi/MLW1kGPo5y0/hqdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Buy @ Drip Irrigation Parts▼ </h4>



<p>Vishwajeet Agro Engineers (Netafim Drip Irrigation Parts) </p>



<p>Mr. Rajesh R. Yadav </p>



<p>+91 9420792424 </p>



<p><a href="https://wa.me/c/919420792424" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://wa.me/c/919420792424</a></p>



<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=53s">0:53</a> Things Required </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=271s">4:31</a> Design and Plan The System </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=456s">7:36</a> Connect The Drip Line Together </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=712s">11:52</a> Anchor Drip Emitter in Container </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=788s">13:08</a> Hide Drip Line Behind the Grow Bag </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=827s">13:47</a> Final Look of Drip Line </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=848s">14:08</a> Plastic Rope to Support Reservoir </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=884s">14:44</a> Test Run of Drip Line </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=954s">15:54</a> Adjust the Drip Line Height </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=1044s">17:24</a> Redesign Reservoir Support System </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLW1kGPo5y0&amp;t=1088s">18:08</a> Final Working of the Drip Line</li></ul>



<h4>Things Required</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-54 wp-block-gallery-53 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" data-id="584"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Things-Required-1.webp" alt="Things Required 1" class="wp-image-584"/><figcaption>Things Required</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<h5>Drip Pipes and Drip Emitter</h5>



<ol><li>16 mm UV Protected HDPE Drip Line<ul><li>This is the main drip irrigation pipe that will supply water to all the drip emitters.</li></ul></li><li>4 mm UV Protected LDPE Feeder Line<ul><li>This pipe from one end is connected to the main 16 mm drip line and on the other end, the drip emitter is attached to your growing container.</li></ul></li><li>Drip Emitter<ul><li>This is the main drip creation device, use a high-quality one that automatically unclogs and creates drops instead of streams.</li></ul></li></ol>



<h5>Water Reservior </h5>



<ol id="block-380bff2d-e321-4d38-b796-4a6cd5f44b57"><li> Two 2 Liter Soda PET Bottle Reservoir<ul><li>We will be using this to store the water for our gravity-fed drip irrigation system.</li></ul></li></ol>



<h5>Connectors</h5>



<ol><li>16 mm Tee Connector  (Optional)<ul><li>This is used when you want to split the main 16mm drip line into different sections.</li></ul></li><li>16 mm Straight Connector<ul><li>This allows for the extension of the 16 mm drip line by connecting the pipe in a straight direction.</li></ul></li><li>16 mm Elbow Connector<ul><li>If you want to bend the 16 mm drip line then this connector is used. </li></ul></li><li>4mm T Connector  (Optional)<ul><li>Using this connector you can attach two 4 mm feeder lines to a single hole in the 16mm drip line.</li></ul></li><li>4mm Pin Connector<ul><li>To connect a single 4 mm feeder line to a hole in the 16 mm drip line use this connector.</li></ul></li></ol>



<h5>Miscellaneous</h5>



<ol><li>Drip Line Hole Punch Tool<ul><li>This is used to punch holes in the main 16 mm drip line to connect the 4 mm feeder line.</li></ul></li><li>Arrow Emitter Stakes<ul><li>This helps to anchor the 4mm feeder line in your growing container. </li></ul></li><li>End Cap<ul><li>This is used to seal the 16 mm drip pipe end to create pressure for the drip irrigation system.</li></ul></li><li>&nbsp;3/4 Inch Screen Filter (Optional)<ul><li>If the water you revive contains a lot of particulate impurities then you will need to filter it using this to prevent clogging the drip emitter. </li></ul></li></ol>



<h4>1. Design and Plan The System</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-56 wp-block-gallery-55 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="586"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Design-and-Plan-The-System.webp" alt="Design and Plan The System" class="wp-image-586"/><figcaption>Design and Plan The System</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Decide your container garden location based on the amount of direct sunlight and the amount of shadow needed depending on ambient temperature.</li><li>I have placed my grow bags facing the east this ensures that it receives full morning sunlight.</li><li>In the evening when it gets very warm in Ahmedabad the terrace parapet wall will provide shade to the plants.</li><li>Decide on the location, height, and support system for your water reservoir.</li><li>Count the number of planters you will be connecting to the drip irrigation system and accordingly calculate the number of drip emitters and length of 4mm feeder pipe required.</li><li>Measure the total length of the 16 mm drip line required to cover your entire growing area and the water reservoir.</li><li>After making all the measurements cut the required length of 16 mm drip pipe and 4 mm feeder pipe. </li></ul>



<h4>2. Connect The Drip Line Together</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-58 wp-block-gallery-57 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="587"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Connect-The-Drip-Line-Together.webp" alt="Connect The Drip Line Together" class="wp-image-587"/><figcaption>Connect The Drip Line Together</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Join the entire drip irrigation system together using the different connectors based on your requirements.</li><li>You can use a cigarette lighter to heat the 16 mm drip pipe slightly to easily insert the fittings without a lot of effort.</li><li>Also, use gloves to protect your hand from blisters caused by excessive friction between the drip pipe and your skin. </li><li>To connect connectors use a rocking motion with a forward push to firmly connect the drip pipe and the connector.</li><li>Using the drip line punch tool create the holes where you want to connect the drip emitter to your planter. </li></ul>



<h4>3. Hide Drip Line Behind the Grow Bag</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-60 wp-block-gallery-59 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="589"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Hide-Drip-Line-Behind-the-Grow-Bag.webp" alt="Hide Drip Line Behind the Grow Bag" class="wp-image-589"/><figcaption>Hide Drip Line Behind the Grow Bag</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Place the drip pipe behind the grow bags to make it more aesthetically pleasing by hiding the pipes from view.</p>



<h4>4. Anchor Drip Emitter in Container</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-62 wp-block-gallery-61 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="588"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Anchor-Drip-Emitter-in-Container.webp" alt="Anchor Drip Emitter in Container" class="wp-image-588"/><figcaption>Anchor Drip Emitter in Container</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Using the arrow emitter stakes firmly attach the drip emitter to the planter.</p>



<h4>5. Plastic Rope to Support Reservoir</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-64 wp-block-gallery-63 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="590"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Plastic-Rope-to-Support-Reservoir.webp" alt="Plastic Rope to Support Reservoir" class="wp-image-590"/><figcaption>Plastic Rope to Support Reservoir</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Use a plastic rope to tie the water reservoir created from a 2-liter PET soda bottle to a supporting structure.</p>



<h4>6. Adjust the Drip Line Height</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-66 wp-block-gallery-65 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="591"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Adjust-the-Drip-Line-Height.webp" alt="Adjust the Drip Line Height" class="wp-image-591"/><figcaption>Adjust the Drip Line Height</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>You might need to adjust the height of your drip pipe and water reservoir to ensure all the drip emitters are working.</li><li>This is because of the small pressure difference created by a gravity-fed drip irrigation system where the reservoir is not placed very high.</li><li>This results in some drippers working whereas others running dry.</li><li>I was able to fix this problem by increasing reservoir height and making sure that the drip pipe height is the same throughout.</li><li>You can support the drip pipe by placing it between the grow bags and the wall.</li></ul>



<h4>7. Redesign Reservoir Support System</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-68 wp-block-gallery-67 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="592"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Redesign-Reservoir-Support-System.webp" alt="Redesign Reservoir Support System" class="wp-image-592"/><figcaption>Redesign Reservoir Support System</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>I have increased the reservoir height by taking support from the concrete design on my terrace parapet</li><li>The second wire provides support to the second 2-liter bottle which is placed on top of the first like a mineral water bottle dispenser system.  </li></ul>



<h4>8. Final Working of the Drip Line</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-70 wp-block-gallery-69 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="593"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Final-Working-of-the-Drip-Line.webp" alt="Final Working of the Drip Line" class="wp-image-593"/><figcaption>Final Working of the Drip Line</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Now fill the reservoir with full 4 liters of water and sit back and enjoy your gravity-fed drip irrigation system.</p>



<p>As the water is emitted from the drippers you will see air bubbles rise in the top mineral water bottle just like what happens in a mineral water bottle dispenser.</p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this step-by-step guide on creating a gravity-fed drip irrigation system for your garden. Hope using this guide you will be able to easily set up your own drip irrigation system. Don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/install-drip-irrigation-system/">How to Install A Drip Irrigation System</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Transplant Seedlings</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/transplant-seedlings/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 06:20:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Growing from Seeds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Vegetables]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Propagation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=566</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this video learn how you can transplant small seedlings grown in a shallow pot into a bigger pot. I will show you using amaranth seedlings but you can do...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/transplant-seedlings/">How to Transplant Seedlings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In this video learn how you can transplant small seedlings grown in a shallow pot into a bigger pot. I will show you using amaranth seedlings but you can do this to any small plants.</p>



<p>I will be transplanting seedlings from my <a href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-cement-planter/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DIY cement planter</a>. But you can use this same method to transplant seedlings from any pot. Ideally, a shallow pot is better for seedling transplantation. </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/transplant-seedlings/"><img src="//i.ytimg.com/vi/2wJ9hcGcC3o/hqdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=119s">1:59</a> Water the Seedlings Thoroughly </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=197s">3:17</a> Plan the Plant Placement </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=223s">3:43</a> Use a Tool to Dig Out Seedlings </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=255s">4:15</a> Remove the Seedlings with Root Ball Intact </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=275s">4:35</a> Repeat the Same Steps </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=335s">5:35</a> Benefits of Mulching </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=427s">7:07</a> Mulching Using Milk Packets </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=518s">8:38</a> Water the Grow Bag Thoroughly </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=542s">9:02</a> Seedling Update After 24 Hrs </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2wJ9hcGcC3o&amp;t=622s">10:22</a> Replace Failed Transplants with Backup Seedlings</li></ul>



<h4>Water the Seedlings Thoroughly </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-72 wp-block-gallery-71 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="567"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Water-the-Seedlings-Thoroughly.webp" alt="Water the Seedlings Thoroughly" class="wp-image-567"/><figcaption>Water the Seedlings Thoroughly</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Before transplanting the seedling make sure to thoroughly moisten the seedlings.</li><li>Doing this will allow us to easily dig out the seedlings.</li><li>Also, the moisture will help the soil to stick to the roots creating our root ball.</li><li>I am using a <a href="https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">DIY Garden sprayer </a>which prevents seedlings from getting disturbed and allows uniform moisture.</li></ul>



<h4>Plan the Plant Placement</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-74 wp-block-gallery-73 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="568"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Plan-the-Plant-Placement.webp" alt="Plan the Plant Placement" class="wp-image-568"/><figcaption>Plan the Plant Placement</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Depending on the type of plant you are growing plan the number of plants and the distance between them.</li><li>For growing Amarnath in containers as a leaf crop, you can grow it in two rows 5 cm apart in a 15 cm wide grow bag.</li></ul>



<h4>Use a Tool to Dig Out Seedlings</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-76 wp-block-gallery-75 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="569"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Use-a-Tool-to-Dig-Out-Seedlings.webp" alt="Use a Tool to Dig Out Seedlings" class="wp-image-569"/><figcaption>Use a Tool to Dig Out Seedlings</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>I will use a small spoon to scoop out seedlings with the root ball intact.</li><li>Place the spoon a few cm away from the seedling stem and press it inside the growing medium.</li><li>Once it reaches the entire depth of the pot apply a gentle upwards force at an angle to scoop out the seedling.</li></ul>



<h4>Remove the Seedlings with Root Ball Intact</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-78 wp-block-gallery-77 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="570"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Remove-the-Seedlings-with-Root-Ball-Intact.webp" alt="Remove the Seedlings with Root Ball Intact" class="wp-image-570"/><figcaption>Remove the Seedlings with Root Ball Intact</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Once the seedling has been loosened out from the container using your hands gently pull it away from the pot.</li><li>If the root ball is coming apart, gently press the root ball to prevent it from breaking.</li></ul>



<h4>Dig a Hole and Gently Place the Seedling</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-80 wp-block-gallery-79 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="571"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Dig-a-Hole-and-Gently-Place-the-Seedling.webp" alt="Dig a Hole and Gently Place the Seedling" class="wp-image-571"/><figcaption>Dig a Hole and Gently Place the Seedling</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Depending on your seedling placement plan dig a hole using your hand.</li><li>Then gently place the transplanted seedling inside the hole.</li><li>Cover the hole with soil and gently press around the seedling stem to support it.</li></ul>



<h4>Add Mulch to Retain Moisture</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-82 wp-block-gallery-81 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="572"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Add-Mulch-to-Retain-Moisture.webp" alt="Add Mulch to Retain Moisture" class="wp-image-572"/><figcaption>Add Mulch to Retain Moisture</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Mulching is very important if you are doing container gardening.</li><li>Mulch not only suppresses weeds but more importantly reduces the soil temperature and helps in retaining soil moisture.</li><li>Mulching can be done using anything which decomposes slowly like dried leaves, dried grass clippings, or straw.</li><li>I am using old milk packets as mulch because it is white which will reflect the sunlight from the soil surface, therefore, reducing the soil temperature. </li><li>Fold the milk packets and using them cover any open soil surface near the seedlings.</li><li>Tuck them inside near the edge of the grow bag to prevent them from flying away.</li></ul>



<h4>Water the Transplants Thoroughly</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-84 wp-block-gallery-83 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="573"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Water-the-Trasnplants-Thoroughly.webp" alt="Water the Trasnplants Thoroughly" class="wp-image-573"/><figcaption>Water the Transplants Thoroughly</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>After transplanting all the seedlings make sure to water them thoroughly. </li><li>This will endure any air gaps between the newly transplanted seedlings and the growing medium is filled up with soil.</li><li>Make sure to water using a fine garden sprayer this will prevent the small sledding from getting dislodged. </li></ul>



<h4>Seedling Update After 24 Hrs</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-86 wp-block-gallery-85 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="574"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Growth-Update-after-24-Hrs.webp" alt="Growth Update after 24 Hrs" class="wp-image-574"/><figcaption>Growth Update after 24 Hrs</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>After 24 hrs you can see most of the transplanted seedlings have survived the critical stage.</li><li>Some of them did not make it this can be because I was not able to get the complete root ball intact for some of the seedlings.</li></ul>



<h4>Replace Failed Transplants with Backup Seedlings</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-88 wp-block-gallery-87 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="575"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Replace-Failed-Transplants-with-Backup-Seedlings.webp" alt="Replace Failed Transplants with Backup Seedlings" class="wp-image-575"/><figcaption>Replace Failed Transplants with Backup Seedlings</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>Always keep some backup seedlings that come in handy plugging the gaps the failed seedlings created.</li><li>Using the same method transplant the backup seedling in place of the failed seedlings.</li></ul>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this step-by-step guide on transplanting seedlings. Hope using this guide you will be able to transplant more seedlings successfully. Don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/transplant-seedlings/">How to Transplant Seedlings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Garden Sprayer Benefits and Making Your Own DIY</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DIY Projects]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing from Seeds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Propagation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=548</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this video learn about the benefits of using a garden sprayer for plant irrigation. Create your own DIY garden sprayer using scrap materials. ▼Scan @ Video Index▼ 00:00 Intro...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/">Garden Sprayer Benefits and Making Your Own DIY</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In this video learn about the benefits of using a garden sprayer for plant irrigation. Create your own DIY garden sprayer using scrap materials. </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/V2F3mB7Hc0g/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=19s">0:19</a> Seed Starting Using Spray Bottle </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=48s">0:48</a> Use Thin Mineral Water Bottle Caps </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=74s">1:14</a> Benefits Of Irrigating using Spray Bottle </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=134s">2:14</a> Irrigating Shallow Pot using Spray Bottle </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=181s">3:01</a> Things Required </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2F3mB7Hc0g&amp;t=228s">3:48</a> Make a Garden Sprayer</li></ul>



<h4>Seed Starting Using Spray Bottle</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Seed-Starting-Using-Spray-Bottle.webp" alt="Seed Starting Using Spray Bottle" class="wp-image-551"/><figcaption>Seed Starting Using Spray Bottle</figcaption></figure>



<p>A spray bottle is very useful in seed starting. Especially if the seeds are tiny. Using the sprayer you can be sure that once seeds are sowed the water will not dislodge them. After the tiny seedling emerges. You can still water them using the spray bottle. This is because the stream of water is so thin that it can not disturb the seedlings.</p>



<h4>Benefits Of Irrigating using Spray Bottle</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-90 wp-block-gallery-89 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="552"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Benefits-Of-Irrigating-using-Spray-Bottle.webp" alt="Benefits Of Irrigating using Spray Bottle" class="wp-image-552"/><figcaption>Benefits Of Irrigating using Spray Bottle</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Using a spray bottle you can uniformly irrigate the soil because the fine spray does not flow away. This means when you spray water in the growing medium it will stay put till it is absorbed by it. Instead of flowing away and causing soil erosion.</p>



<h4>Irrigating Shallow Pot using Spray Bottle</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-92 wp-block-gallery-91 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="553"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Irrigating-Shallow-Pot-using-Spray-Bottle.webp" alt="Irrigating Shallow Pot using Spray Bottle" class="wp-image-553"/><figcaption>Irrigating Shallow Pot using Spray Bottle</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Using a garden sprayer also comes in handy when you need to water pots that do not have the depth for water to stand. The gentle water spray generated from the sprayer allows the water to be absorbed by the growing medium slowly. This prevents water from overflowing the pot and causing soil erosion.</p>



<h4>Things Required</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-94 wp-block-gallery-93 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="554"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Things-Required.webp" alt="Things Required" class="wp-image-554"/><figcaption>Things Required</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ul><li>You will need a <strong>Soda PET bottle</strong> you can use any size 2 l or 500 ml depending on how big you want your spray bottle to be.</li><li>You will need a<strong> mineral water bottle cap</strong> because this is made from thin plastic you can easily make holes in it using a pin.</li><li>Lastly, you will need a <strong>pin or needle</strong> the thinner the tip the better.</li></ul>



<h4>Make a Garden Sprayer</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-96 wp-block-gallery-95 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="555"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Make-a-Garden-Sprayer.webp" alt="Make a Garden Sprayer" class="wp-image-555"/><figcaption>Make a Garden Sprayer</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>Remove the soda bottle cap and screw in the mineral water bottle cap.</li><li>Now using the pin pierce holes in the mineral water bottle cap.</li><li>Be careful not to overlap two holes.</li><li>Keep creating holes using the needle till the full surface area is covered.</li></ol>



<p>That&#8217;s it you have now created your own DIY spray bottle. To use it simply fill the bottle with water. Invert the bottle and press it till you see a shower coming out from the cap. </p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this DIY project of converting trash into gardening supplies. Using this guide you can also make your own gardening spray bottle. Don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/diy-sprayer/">Garden Sprayer Benefits and Making Your Own DIY</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Grow Arabian Jasmine Mogra from Cuttings</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/jasmine-cutting/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Growing Flowering Plants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing from Cuttings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Plants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plant Propagation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi friends in this video learn how you can propagate Arabian Jasmine from stem cutting. Jasmine is a tropical plant and it has got several different varieties. The variety that...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/jasmine-cutting/">How to Grow Arabian Jasmine Mogra from Cuttings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi friends in this video learn how you can propagate Arabian Jasmine from stem cutting. Jasmine is a tropical plant and it has got several different varieties. The variety that we&#8217;ll be talking about is Arabian jasmine. Arabian jasmine is a native species of tropical Asia. It grows natively in south Asia as well as southeast Asia. It is the national flower of Indonesia as well as the Philippines.</p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/jasmine-cutting/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/OurmjFGVPns/hqdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=10s">0:10</a> Jasmine Plant Information </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=139s">2:19</a> Reasons for Propagating </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=243s">4:03</a> Select Jasmine Stem for Cutting </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=392s">6:32</a> Prepare Jasmine Cuttings </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=573s">9:33</a> Cutting Growing Conditions </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=671s">11:11</a> Cutting Growing Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=712s">11:52</a> Rooting Hormone </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=738s">12:18</a> Create Humidity Dome Supports </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=787s">13:07</a> Hydrate the Rooting Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=809s">13:29</a> Add Cutting in Rooting Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OurmjFGVPns&amp;t=913s">15:13</a> Add Plastic Bag Humidity Dome</li></ul>



<h4>Jasmine Plant Information</h4>



<p>In India, it is used in wedding ceremonies as a garland. In addition, it is used in hair decoration the Hindi term for it is called Gajara. It&#8217;s used to decorate the hair buns. As well as it&#8217;s a sacred flower so it is offered to the gods during worship.  </p>



<p>Arabian jasmine has got a beautiful smell. Perfumes, as well as herbal tea, are made using jasmine flowers. The jasmine tea is made using freshly plucked flowers which are mixed with green tea leaves. Over one week, Tea leaves absorb the scent of the jasmine flower. After that, the jasmine flower is separated from the tea leaves. This is then sold as jasmine tea.</p>



<p>The Hindi name for jasmine is mogra. Jasmine can only be propagated via cutting. As it does not produce any seeds or any fruit for that matter. I will show you how you can propagate Arabian jasmine in a very hot and dry climate.  We are based located in India in Ahmedabad which has got an arid subtropical climate. At present, the average day&#8217;s high temperature is around 42°C. But in the coming days, it has been projected to go as high as 44 °C. Given such bad weather, I&#8217;ll show you how you can still propagate Jasmine from cutting by taking proper precautions.  So without wasting much time let&#8217;s get started&#8230;</p>



<h4>Reasons for Propagating</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-98 wp-block-gallery-97 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="542"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Reasons-for-Propagating.webp" alt="Reasons for Propagating" class="wp-image-542"/><figcaption>Reasons for Propagating</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Okay friends this is my jasmine plant. As you can see it&#8217;s not very dense. It&#8217;s quite old it&#8217;s around five to six years old plant. Previously it used to get very bushy and used to flower a lot. Every year we used to cut it back and it used to grow double the size. But now the stems have grown quite old. In fact, in some of them, the termite has also infected it. So the first reason for propagating it is to save this plant and give it a new life. </p>



<p>One more issue with this plant is it flowers for only 2 months in the whole year. I suspect this is because of its location. The plant is placed facing the north and so only receives full sun in March and April.  In the winter season, it does not receive any direct sunlight. I think due to this it does not bloom in the winters. So the second reason for propagating this plant from cutting is to change its location. Hopefully, that will make it bloom for a longer period. So let&#8217;s start the process.</p>



<h4>Select Jasmine Stem for Cutting</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-100 wp-block-gallery-99 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="531"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Select-Jasmine-Stem-for-Cutting.webp" alt="Select Jasmine Stem for Cutting" class="wp-image-531"/><figcaption>Select Jasmine Stem for Cutting</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>You can grow jasmine plants by cutting using softwood as well as semi-hardwood stem cutting. Softwood stem is new growth that is completely green in color and is very flexible. Whereas semi-hardwood stem is greenish-brown in color. They are also quite firm and can not be bent without breaking. Hardwood stem is a more than 2 years old stem that is very firm and thick. </p>



<p>Rooting using softwood stem cuttings is easier. But plants developed from semi-hardwood cutting are stronger. They also bloom much quicker than plants grown from softwood cutting. I will take a stem cutting from both semi-hardwood and softwood. Cut the stem right below the node region. The node region is where a leaf comes out from the stem. The length of the cutting should be around 8-10 inches. After cutting the stems make sure to place them in water so that it is kept moist.</p>



<h4>Prepare Jasmine Cuttings</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-102 wp-block-gallery-101 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="532"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Prepare-Jasmine-Cuttings.webp" alt="Prepare Jasmine Cuttings" class="wp-image-532"/><figcaption>Prepare Jasmine Cuttings</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>To prepare a jasmine stem for cutting you need to first remove the growing tips. Then remove any flowers or buds present on it. This ensures the stem does not waste its energy in shoot and flower growth. All the energy is now utilized in root development. </p>



<p>Next, remove the lower leaves to expose the 2 nodes. The node region is where the root development is most likely to start. This is because the node region has got unspecialized cells. This means depending upon the environment the node region can develop a new branch, new leaf, or a new root. So by placing 2 nodes under the soil. You are doing your chances of root development.</p>



<p>Next cut the leaves in half using scissors or hands. This will reduce water loss from the pores present at the bottom of the leaves. It will also reduce the space requirement in your humidity dome. </p>



<h4>Cutting Growing Conditions</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-104 wp-block-gallery-103 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="533"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Cutting-Growing-Conditions.webp" alt="Cutting Growing Conditions" class="wp-image-533"/><figcaption>Cutting Growing Conditions</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>To grow plants from cutting you need to place them in a suitable growing environment. They should be placed in a place that has very high humidity. The temperature range should be 25-30°C and bright indirect sunlight is required. To achieve this I will place the cuttings facing the north. At this location, it will receive bright diffused sunlight reflected from our house wall. If you are growing in a dry climate you will also need to add a humidity dome. You can easily create a humidity dome from a plastic soda pet bottle. Simply cut the bottom part of the 2-liter soda pet bottle. Cover your pot with this pet bottle without the cap. The hole at the top allows the hot air to escape. The lighter humid air settles down in the cutting growing region.  You can also create a humidity dome using plastic polythene bags. I will show you how to do it later on in this article. </p>



<h4>Cutting Growing Medium</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-106 wp-block-gallery-105 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="534"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Cutting-Growing-Medium.webp" alt="Cutting Growing Medium" class="wp-image-534"/><figcaption>Cutting Growing Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>To grow cuttings the rooting medium should be light, fast-draining, and inert. Perlite checks all these boxes so we will be using it for rooting our jasmine cuttings. Other alternatives can be peat moss, coco peat, and river sand. All these are inert which means it does not support the growth of fungus and bacteria. Because the cuttings initially do not have a root system. They are vulnerable to fungus and bacteria infection. It is essential to select a medium that inhibits the growth of these pathogens. </p>



<h4>Create Humidity Dome Supports</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-108 wp-block-gallery-107 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="535"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Create-Humidity-Dome-Supports.webp" alt="Create Humidity Dome Supports" class="wp-image-535"/><figcaption>Create Humidity Dome Supports</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Now let&#8217;s start creating our humidity dome from a plastic bag. First, we need some kind of support for the plastic bag. This will make sure that the plastic bag does not touch the cuttings. In addition, it will prevent the plastic bag from collapsing with the wind. For the support take three sticks of equal length. They should be long enough to prevent the plastic bag from touching the cuttings. Insert the sticks in a triangular shape to provide support in all three directions. Next, we need to water the rooting medium.</p>



<h4>Hydrate the Rooting Medium</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-110 wp-block-gallery-109 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="536"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Hydrate-the-Rooting-Medium.webp" alt="Hydrate the Rooting Medium" class="wp-image-536"/><figcaption>Hydrate the Rooting Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Using fine shower water the rooting medium thoroughly. Water it till you see water dripping out from the bottom of the pot. Once that happens you are sure that it&#8217;s completely saturated with water. </p>



<h4>Add Cutting in Rooting Medium</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-112 wp-block-gallery-111 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="537"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Add-Cutting-in-Rooting-Medium.webp" alt="Add Cutting in Rooting Medium" class="wp-image-537"/><figcaption>Add Cutting in Rooting Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Use a pencil or your finger to create holes in the rooting medium. If you are growing a semi-hardwood cutting you should use a rooting hormone. The rooting hormone stimulates root development. It increases the chances of successful cutting root growth. Adding rooting hormone to your cutting is quite simple. Dip the rooting end of the cutting in water. Then dip the cutting in the rooting hormone powder which will stick to it. Tap the cutting to remove excess rooting hormone powder. Place the cutting in the hole created previously. Using your fingers firm up the rooting medium around the cutting. Repeat the step for the remaining cuttings. Once all the cuttings are placed in the rooting medium. Water it thoroughly so that all the air gaps between the cutting and rooting medium are filled with water. </p>



<h4>Add Plastic Bag Humidity Dome</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-114 wp-block-gallery-113 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="538"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Add-Plastic-Bag-Humidity-Dome.webp" alt="Add Plastic Bag Humidity Dome" class="wp-image-538"/><figcaption>Add Plastic Bag Humidity Dome</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Okay, now the last step is to add the plastic humidity dome. I will use two plastic bags to create the humidity dome. One plastic bag will cover it from the bottom and the other from the top. I am using two polybags because I do not have a single big enough plastic bag to cover it completely from the top. To add the bottom plastic bag roll it and place the pot in the middle. Now unroll to the top and support it using the sticks. Now add the second plastic bag similarly from the top. Roll the plastic bag and place it on the stick supports. Now from the top unroll it downwards to overlap the bottom plastic bag. Now create a small went at the top by making a hole. Add a mineral water bottle top to support the went in place.</p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this detailed step-by-step guide. Showing how to grow Arabian jasmine Mogra from cuttings at your home. If yes, don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family whom you think could benefit from it. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/jasmine-cutting/">How to Grow Arabian Jasmine Mogra from Cuttings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Make Bone Meal at Home</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DIY Projects]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organic Fertilizers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=503</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this video learn how to make bone meal fertilizer at your home. Convert your kitchen waste into invaluable organic slow-release bone meal fertilizer. ▼Watch @ Related Video▼ What is...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/">How to Make Bone Meal at Home</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In this video learn how to make bone meal fertilizer at your home. Convert your kitchen waste into invaluable organic slow-release bone meal fertilizer.  </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/i-91oR32H_g/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Watch @ Related Video▼ </h4>



<p><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/bone-meal/">What is Bone Meal? How to Use it? </a></p>



<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=0s">0:00</a> Intro</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=54s">0:54</a> Dry Bones in Sun for 15 days</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=103s">1:43</a> Working of Solar Dehydrator</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=171s">2:51</a> Manually Break Bones to Small Size</li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=361s">6:01</a> Crush Bones to Powder Using Grinder </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=444s">7:24</a> Filter Crushed Bone to Get Bone Meal </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i-91oR32H_g&amp;t=486s">8:06</a> Repeat the Process</li></ul>



<h4>Solar Dehydrator Working Principle</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-116 wp-block-gallery-115 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="510"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Working-of-Solar-Dehydrator.webp" alt="Working of Solar Dehydrator" class="wp-image-510" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Working-of-Solar-Dehydrator.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Working-of-Solar-Dehydrator-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Working-of-Solar-Dehydrator-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Working-of-Solar-Dehydrator-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Working-of-Solar-Dehydrator-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Working of Solar Dehydrator</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>The solar dehydrator is black in color to absorb the maximum amount of sunlight.</li><li>The inclination of the solar dehydrtor allows the moist lighter air to escape from the top.</li><li>The dry air is fed in from the vents at the bottom of the box.</li><li>In direct sunlight the contents of the box is heated up and releases moisture in the air.</li><li>This moist air rises to the top and escapes out from the vents leaving dry air behind.</li><li>Over time this process is repeated and slowly the contents of the box get dehydrated.</li></ol>



<h4>1 Dry Bones in Sun for 15 days</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-118 wp-block-gallery-117 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="511"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dry-Bones-in-Sun-for-15-days.webp" alt="Dry Bones in Sun for 15 days" class="wp-image-511" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dry-Bones-in-Sun-for-15-days.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dry-Bones-in-Sun-for-15-days-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dry-Bones-in-Sun-for-15-days-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dry-Bones-in-Sun-for-15-days-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Dry-Bones-in-Sun-for-15-days-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Dry Bones in Sun for 15 days</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>Collect the bones from your kitchen scraps and place them in a solar dehydrator for 15 days.</li><li>If you do not have a solar dehydrator you can use an oven or an electric dehydrator or even a pressure cooker.</li><li>By dehydrating the bones it becomes brittle and is easy to crush into a powder.</li></ol>



<h4>2 Manually Break Bones to Small Size</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-120 wp-block-gallery-119 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="509"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Manually-Break-Bones-to-Small-Size.webp" alt="Manually Break Bones to Small Size" class="wp-image-509" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Manually-Break-Bones-to-Small-Size.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Manually-Break-Bones-to-Small-Size-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Manually-Break-Bones-to-Small-Size-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Manually-Break-Bones-to-Small-Size-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Manually-Break-Bones-to-Small-Size-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Manually Break Bones to Small Size</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>Once the bones are dehydrated bring them inside and cover them with a plastic sack</li><li>Cush the bones into smaller pieces using stones</li><li>Then open the plastic sac and check for any large bone fragments</li><li>Use the stones to break them into smaller pieces</li><li>You can also use mortar and piston to break them into smaller chunks</li></ol>



<h4>3 Crush Bones to Powder Using Grinder</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-122 wp-block-gallery-121 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="507"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Crush-Bones-to-Powder-Using-Grinder.webp" alt="Crush Bones to Powder Using Grinder" class="wp-image-507" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Crush-Bones-to-Powder-Using-Grinder.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Crush-Bones-to-Powder-Using-Grinder-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Crush-Bones-to-Powder-Using-Grinder-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Crush-Bones-to-Powder-Using-Grinder-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Crush-Bones-to-Powder-Using-Grinder-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Crush Bones to Powder Using Grinder</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>Using an electric blender crush the bones into fine powder.</li><li>Make sure not to add too many bone pieces at once to prevent motor overload.</li></ol>



<h4>4 Filter Crushed Bone to Get Bone Meal</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-124 wp-block-gallery-123 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="505"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Filter-Crushed-Bone-to-Get-Bone-Meal.webp" alt="Filter Crushed Bone to Get Bone Meal" class="wp-image-505" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Filter-Crushed-Bone-to-Get-Bone-Meal.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Filter-Crushed-Bone-to-Get-Bone-Meal-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Filter-Crushed-Bone-to-Get-Bone-Meal-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Filter-Crushed-Bone-to-Get-Bone-Meal-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Filter-Crushed-Bone-to-Get-Bone-Meal-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Filter Crushed Bone to Get Bone Meal</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>To make a fine bone meal powder use a metal mesh to filter out the larger bone fragments.</li><li>Then again crush the coarse bone powder to get a fine powder.</li><li>Repeat the steps till all your bones have been crushed to a fine powder. </li></ol>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this guide to making bone meal fertilizer at your home. If yes, don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family whom you think could benefit from it. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/">How to Make Bone Meal at Home</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Grow Fenugreek/Methi From Seeds</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/grow-fenugreek-methi/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 11:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Growing from Seeds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Herbs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Growing Your Own Food]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=482</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi friends in this video I will show how I grew fenugreek plants from seeds. I will show you the plant growth updates across its entire life cycle. From seed...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/grow-fenugreek-methi/">How to Grow Fenugreek/Methi From Seeds</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi friends in this video I will show how I grew fenugreek plants from seeds. I will show you the plant growth updates across its entire life cycle. From seed germination to seed pod formation. So make sure to watch the complete video. </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/grow-fenugreek-methi/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/fS8QfG_6enE/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=31s">0:31</a> Seed Sowing </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=163s">2:43</a> Seed Germination After 6 Days </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=194s">3:14</a> Thinning of Seedlings After 8 Days </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=258s">4:18</a> Seedling Transplantation After 15 Days </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=279s">4:39</a> Preparation of Growing Medium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=325s">5:25</a> Growing Container </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=343s">5:43</a> Seedling Transplantation </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=465s">7:45</a> MethiGrowing Conditions Weather </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=499s">8:19</a> Mature Fenugreek Plant After 1 Month </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=546s">9:06</a> Fenugreek Flowering After 1.5 Months </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=588s">9:48</a> Fenugreek Leaf Harvesting </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fS8QfG_6enE&amp;t=635s">10:35</a> Fenugreek Seed Pods After 2 Months</li></ul>



<h4>Seed Sowing </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-126 wp-block-gallery-125 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="483"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Sowing.webp" alt="Seed Sowing" class="wp-image-483" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Sowing.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Sowing-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Sowing-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Sowing-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Sowing-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Seed Sowing</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<ol><li>Pre-Soak the seeds in water for 3-4 hrs.</li><li>Moisten the seedling container</li><li>Create a hole and place 3 seeds in each hole</li><li>Cover the hole keep it moist till the seeds germinate</li></ol>



<h4>Seed Germination After 6 Days </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-128 wp-block-gallery-127 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="484"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Germination-After-6-Days.webp" alt="Seed Germination After 6 Days" class="wp-image-484" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Germination-After-6-Days.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Germination-After-6-Days-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Germination-After-6-Days-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Germination-After-6-Days-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seed-Germination-After-6-Days-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Seed Germination After 6 Days</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Seeds should germinate 3-7 days in ideal growing conditions </p>



<h4>Thinning of Seedlings After 8 Days </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-130 wp-block-gallery-129 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="485"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Thinning-of-Seedlings-After-8-Days.webp" alt="Thinning of Seedlings After 8 Days" class="wp-image-485" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Thinning-of-Seedlings-After-8-Days.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Thinning-of-Seedlings-After-8-Days-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Thinning-of-Seedlings-After-8-Days-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Thinning-of-Seedlings-After-8-Days-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Thinning-of-Seedlings-After-8-Days-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Thinning of Seedlings After 8 Days</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>In containers where multiple seeds have germinated remove the weaker plants. This will make the stronger plant thrive. Using a pair of scissors cut the stem of the extra plant from the soil base.</p>



<h4>Seedling Transplantation After 15 Days </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-132 wp-block-gallery-131 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="486"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Ready-For-Transplantation-After-15-Days.webp" alt="Seedling Ready For Transplantation After 15 Days" class="wp-image-486" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Ready-For-Transplantation-After-15-Days.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Ready-For-Transplantation-After-15-Days-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Ready-For-Transplantation-After-15-Days-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Ready-For-Transplantation-After-15-Days-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Ready-For-Transplantation-After-15-Days-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Seedling Ready For Transplantation After 15 Days</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The seedling should be ready for transplantation in 10-15 days of sowing. As we used paper pots we can see the roots have come out from the bottom. This is an indication that you can transplant them in their final growing container.</p>



<h4>Preparation of Growing Medium </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-134 wp-block-gallery-133 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="487"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Preparation-of-Growing-Medium.webp" alt="Preparation of Growing Medium" class="wp-image-487" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Preparation-of-Growing-Medium.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Preparation-of-Growing-Medium-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Preparation-of-Growing-Medium-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Preparation-of-Growing-Medium-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Preparation-of-Growing-Medium-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Preparation of Growing Medium</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The growing medium is a mix of 50% Homemade Kitchen Compost and 40% Garden Soil and 10% perlite. Perlite improves the overall structure of the potting mix. It prevents soil compaction and increases the air in the medium.</p>



<h4>Growing Container </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-136 wp-block-gallery-135 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="488"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Growing-Container.webp" alt="Growing Container" class="wp-image-488" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Growing-Container.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Growing-Container-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Growing-Container-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Growing-Container-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Growing-Container-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Growing Container</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>I will be planting them in this hanging pot. This hanging planter is around 5 inches deep and 10 cm wide. Which is good enough for growing fenugreek because of its shallow root system.  Place some stone at the bottom to cover the drainage holes. This improves drainage and prevents soil from dripping out.</p>



<h4>Seedling Transplantation </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-138 wp-block-gallery-137 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="489"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Transplantation.webp" alt="Seedling Transplantation" class="wp-image-489" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Transplantation.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Transplantation-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Transplantation-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Transplantation-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Seedling-Transplantation-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Seedling Transplantation</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>You can place seven fenugreek plants in this hanging pot. Make sure to space them out so that they grow nicely. The paper pots will decompose over time so no need to remove them. After transplanting tap the pot gently to remove air gaps. Water it thoroughly using a spray bottle.</p>



<h4>Methi Growing Conditions Weather </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-140 wp-block-gallery-139 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="490"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Growing-Conditions-Weather.webp" alt="Fenugreek Growing Conditions Weather" class="wp-image-490" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Growing-Conditions-Weather.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Growing-Conditions-Weather-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Growing-Conditions-Weather-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Growing-Conditions-Weather-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Growing-Conditions-Weather-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Fenugreek Growing Conditions Weather</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>Methi grows in the winter season here in Ahmedabad, Gujarat. But the general growing temperature range is 25-30 degrees C. It likes a dry climate arid climate. You can grow fenugreek in an arid summer climate with 40+ degrees C temperature by planting them in indirect sunlight.</p>



<h4>Mature Fenugreek Plant After 1 Month </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-142 wp-block-gallery-141 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="491"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Mature-Fenugreek-Plant-After-1-Month.webp" alt="Mature Fenugreek Plant After 1 Month" class="wp-image-491" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Mature-Fenugreek-Plant-After-1-Month.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Mature-Fenugreek-Plant-After-1-Month-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Mature-Fenugreek-Plant-After-1-Month-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Mature-Fenugreek-Plant-After-1-Month-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Mature-Fenugreek-Plant-After-1-Month-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Mature Fenugreek Plant After 1 Month</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>After 1 month the Methi plant has grown a bit tall. The true leaves have come. It has got trifoliate levels. You can start harvesting the leaves now.</p>



<h4>Fenugreek Flowering After 1.5 Months </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-144 wp-block-gallery-143 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="492"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Flowering-After-1.5-Months.webp" alt="Fenugreek Flowering After 1.5 Months" class="wp-image-492" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Flowering-After-1.5-Months.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Flowering-After-1.5-Months-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Flowering-After-1.5-Months-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Flowering-After-1.5-Months-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Flowering-After-1.5-Months-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Fenugreek Flowering After 1.5 Months</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>After 1.5 months the plant has now gone into the flowering stage. The flowers are initially white in color when they bloom. At the end of the day, they change color to yellow. </p>



<h4>Fenugreek Leaf Harvesting </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-146 wp-block-gallery-145 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="493"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Leaf-Harvesting.webp" alt="Fenugreek Leaf Harvesting" class="wp-image-493" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Leaf-Harvesting.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Leaf-Harvesting-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Leaf-Harvesting-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Leaf-Harvesting-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Leaf-Harvesting-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Fenugreek Leaf Harvesting</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>To harvest fenugreek leaves, cut the stem 1 inch above the ground. This will ensure that it regrows for a second harvest after 15 days. You can then separate the leaves from the stem.</p>



<h4>Fenugreek Seed Pods After 2 Months</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-148 wp-block-gallery-147 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="494"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Seed-Pods-After-2-Months.webp" alt="Fenugreek Seed Pods After 2 Months" class="wp-image-494" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Seed-Pods-After-2-Months.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Seed-Pods-After-2-Months-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Seed-Pods-After-2-Months-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Seed-Pods-After-2-Months-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Fenugreek-Seed-Pods-After-2-Months-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Fenugreek Seed Pods After 2 Months</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p>The seeds can be harvested after the seed pod turns brown in color. This usually takes around 3 months from sowing. This is what the immature seed pods look like.</p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this post about growing fenugreek/methi at your home. If yes, don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family whom you think could benefit from it. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/grow-fenugreek-methi/">How to Grow Fenugreek/Methi From Seeds</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is Bone Meal? Benefits Making Application</title>
		<link>https://plantsmylove.com/bone-meal/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Mahaseth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DIY Projects]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Organic Fertilizers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://plantsmylove.com/?p=456</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi, friends in this video we will look at Bone Meal Organic Fertilizer. We will see What it is? What are the benefits of it? How it is made? and...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/bone-meal/">What is Bone Meal? Benefits Making Application</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hi, friends in this video we will look at Bone Meal Organic Fertilizer. We will see What it is? What are the benefits of it? How it is made? and How to apply it? </p>


<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube"><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/bone-meal/"><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/u2bVaYmnE7A/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="YouTube Video"></a><br /><br /><figcaption></figcaption></figure>


<h4>▼Scan @ Video Index▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=40s">0:40</a> Homemade Bone Meal Powder </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=74s">1:14</a> Role of Phosphorus in Plant Life Cycle </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=126s">2:06</a> Amending Soil with Bone Meal </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=183s">3:03</a> Sun Drying Bones in DIY Solar Dryer </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=263s">4:23</a> Crushing Bone to Bone Meal Powder </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=294s">4:54</a> Benefits of Making your Bone Meal </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=341s">5:41</a> Bone Meal NPK </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=371s">6:11</a> Stone Tools for Bone Crushing </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=414s">6:54</a> Bone Meal Application to Adenium </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=499s">8:19</a> Bone Meal Application to Papaya Tree </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=564s">9:24</a> Bone Meal Application to Desert Rose </li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u2bVaYmnE7A&amp;t=634s">10:34</a> Bone Meal Application to Yellow Trumpetbush</li></ul>



<h4>▼Watch @ Related Video▼ </h4>



<ul><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-bone-meal/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How to Make Bone Meal</a></li><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/how-to-make-homemade-compost/">How to Make Kitchen Compost</a></li><li><a href="https://plantsmylove.com/make-banana-peel-fertilizer/">How to Make Banna Peel Fertilizer </a></li></ul>



<h4><br>Homemade Bone Meal Powder</h4>



<p>Bone meal is crushed animal bones that have been sterilized by heat treatment to kill any harmful pathogen. This powder when applied to plants acts as a slow-release fertilizer. Bone meal is rich in phosphorous and calcium both of which play a significant role in plant growth lifecycle. You can make bone meal fertilizer in your home quite easily. </p>



<figure class="wp-container-150 wp-block-gallery-149 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="477"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Home-Made-Bone-Meal-Fertilizer-Rich-in-Phosphorus-1024x576.webp" alt="Home Made Bone Meal Fertilizer Rich in Phosphorus" class="wp-image-477" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Home-Made-Bone-Meal-Fertilizer-Rich-in-Phosphorus-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Home-Made-Bone-Meal-Fertilizer-Rich-in-Phosphorus-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Home-Made-Bone-Meal-Fertilizer-Rich-in-Phosphorus-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Home-Made-Bone-Meal-Fertilizer-Rich-in-Phosphorus-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Home-Made-Bone-Meal-Fertilizer-Rich-in-Phosphorus.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Home Made Bone Meal Fertilizer Rich in Phosphorus and Calcium</figcaption></figure>
<figcaption class="blocks-gallery-caption">FInely crushed chicken and goat bones</figcaption></figure>



<h4><br>Role of Phosphorus in Plant Life Cycle </h4>



<p>Phosphorous is an important plant nutrient. It is used for the all-round development of the plant. Using phosphorous plants stores the energy created from the photosynthesis process. Soil rich in phosphorous allow plants to develop a stronger root system and increase yield. It also improves the disease resistance of plants. Plants deficient in phosphorous do not show any visible symptoms except for decreased overall yield. Add phosphorous fertilizer to root tubers like carrot, potatoes, sweet potato, radish, etc increase yield. Also flowering and fruiting plants benefit from amending the soil with phosphorus-rich fertilizer.</p>



<h4>Amending Soil with Bone Meal </h4>



<p>Most soils are deficient in phosphorous so it is essential to amend the soil with phosphorus-rich fertilizer like bone meal. The bone meal being an organic fertilizer is a slow-release fertilizer. In a time frame of 3 -4 months, the plant nutrient gets slowly available.  This happens when the soil microbes and the soil acids slowly break the bone powder into water-soluble phosphorus plant nutrients. </p>



<h4>Sun Drying Bones in DIY Solar Dryer </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-152 wp-block-gallery-151 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="461"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Solar-Dryer-Made-From-Laptop-Box-Used-For-Drying-Bones-1024x576.webp" alt="DIY Solar Dryer Made From Laptop Box Used For Drying Bones" class="wp-image-461" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Solar-Dryer-Made-From-Laptop-Box-Used-For-Drying-Bones-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Solar-Dryer-Made-From-Laptop-Box-Used-For-Drying-Bones-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Solar-Dryer-Made-From-Laptop-Box-Used-For-Drying-Bones-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Solar-Dryer-Made-From-Laptop-Box-Used-For-Drying-Bones-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Solar-Dryer-Made-From-Laptop-Box-Used-For-Drying-Bones.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>DIY Solar Dryer Made From Laptop Box Used For Drying Bones</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="459"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-One-side-of-the-Cardboard-is-Cut-and-a-transparent-Plastic-Sheet-is-Attached-1024x576.webp" alt="One side of the Cardboard is Cut and a transparent Plastic Sheet is Attached" class="wp-image-459" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-One-side-of-the-Cardboard-is-Cut-and-a-transparent-Plastic-Sheet-is-Attached-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-One-side-of-the-Cardboard-is-Cut-and-a-transparent-Plastic-Sheet-is-Attached-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-One-side-of-the-Cardboard-is-Cut-and-a-transparent-Plastic-Sheet-is-Attached-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-One-side-of-the-Cardboard-is-Cut-and-a-transparent-Plastic-Sheet-is-Attached-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-One-side-of-the-Cardboard-is-Cut-and-a-transparent-Plastic-Sheet-is-Attached.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>One side of the Cardboard is Cut and a transparent Plastic Sheet is Attached</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="463"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Sun-Light-Goes-Inside-and-the-Black-Color-Absorb-the-Solar-Radiation-and-Heats-the-Air--1024x576.webp" alt="Sun Light Goes Inside and the Black Color Absorb the Solar Radiation and Heats the Air" class="wp-image-463" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Sun-Light-Goes-Inside-and-the-Black-Color-Absorb-the-Solar-Radiation-and-Heats-the-Air--1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Sun-Light-Goes-Inside-and-the-Black-Color-Absorb-the-Solar-Radiation-and-Heats-the-Air--300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Sun-Light-Goes-Inside-and-the-Black-Color-Absorb-the-Solar-Radiation-and-Heats-the-Air--768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Sun-Light-Goes-Inside-and-the-Black-Color-Absorb-the-Solar-Radiation-and-Heats-the-Air--800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Sun-Light-Goes-Inside-and-the-Black-Color-Absorb-the-Solar-Radiation-and-Heats-the-Air-.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Sun Light Goes Inside and the Black Color Absorb the Solar Radiation and Heats the Air</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="462"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/4-It-is-Placed-at-an-Angle-so-that-hot-air-rises-and-escapes-out-from-the-vents-1024x576.webp" alt="It is Placed at an Angle so that hot air rises and escapes out from the vents" class="wp-image-462" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/4-It-is-Placed-at-an-Angle-so-that-hot-air-rises-and-escapes-out-from-the-vents-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/4-It-is-Placed-at-an-Angle-so-that-hot-air-rises-and-escapes-out-from-the-vents-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/4-It-is-Placed-at-an-Angle-so-that-hot-air-rises-and-escapes-out-from-the-vents-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/4-It-is-Placed-at-an-Angle-so-that-hot-air-rises-and-escapes-out-from-the-vents-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/4-It-is-Placed-at-an-Angle-so-that-hot-air-rises-and-escapes-out-from-the-vents.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>It is Placed at an Angle so that hot air rises and escapes out from the vents</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="460"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-All-the-chicken-and-goat-bone-placed-inside-gets-dried-in-15-days-1024x576.webp" alt="All the chicken and goat bone placed inside gets dried in 15 days" class="wp-image-460" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-All-the-chicken-and-goat-bone-placed-inside-gets-dried-in-15-days-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-All-the-chicken-and-goat-bone-placed-inside-gets-dried-in-15-days-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-All-the-chicken-and-goat-bone-placed-inside-gets-dried-in-15-days-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-All-the-chicken-and-goat-bone-placed-inside-gets-dried-in-15-days-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-All-the-chicken-and-goat-bone-placed-inside-gets-dried-in-15-days.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>All the chicken and goat bone placed inside gets dried in 15 days</figcaption></figure>
<figcaption class="blocks-gallery-caption">Drying chicken and Goat Bones Using a DIY Solar Dryer</figcaption></figure>



<p>It takes around 15 days to sun dry the bones in the solar dehydrator. Once dried the bones become extremely brittle and then can be crushed easily.</p>



<h4>Crushing Bone to Bone Meal Powder </h4>



<p>The first step to creating bonemeal depends on how you want to make them brittle. There are multiple ways of doing it. You can sun-dry or use an oven or use an electric dehydrator you can even pressure cook them for an hour. The result is the same you get bones which is very easy to break. Once you have dried them you can use some tools to break them into smaller chunks. Use a food processor or hand blender to crush them into a fine powder.   </p>



<h4>Benefits of Making your Bone Meal </h4>



<p>You can convert garbage from your home to very useful plant nutrients which will increase plant yield. A store-bought bone meal might contain harmful contaminants like heavy metals and bacteria.  The biggest advantage is it&#8217;s completely free to make a bone meal at home.</p>



<h4>Bone Meal NPK <br></h4>



<p>On average bone meal has an NPK of 3:15:0 and has 12% calcium content. </p>



<h4>Stone Tools for Bone Crushing <br></h4>



<figure class="wp-container-154 wp-block-gallery-153 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-2 is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="464"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Mortar-and-Piston-Using-River-Stones-.webp" alt="DIY Mortar and Piston Using River Stones" class="wp-image-464" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Mortar-and-Piston-Using-River-Stones-.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Mortar-and-Piston-Using-River-Stones--300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Mortar-and-Piston-Using-River-Stones--1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Mortar-and-Piston-Using-River-Stones--768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-DIY-Mortar-and-Piston-Using-River-Stones--800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>DIY Mortar and Piston Using River Stones</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="465"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Bone-is-placed-on-the-flat-stone-and-is-crushed-when-hit-by-the-other-stone.webp" alt="Bone is placed on the flat stone and is crushed when hit by the other stone" class="wp-image-465" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Bone-is-placed-on-the-flat-stone-and-is-crushed-when-hit-by-the-other-stone.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Bone-is-placed-on-the-flat-stone-and-is-crushed-when-hit-by-the-other-stone-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Bone-is-placed-on-the-flat-stone-and-is-crushed-when-hit-by-the-other-stone-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Bone-is-placed-on-the-flat-stone-and-is-crushed-when-hit-by-the-other-stone-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Bone-is-placed-on-the-flat-stone-and-is-crushed-when-hit-by-the-other-stone-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Bone is placed on the flat stone and is crushed when hit by the other stone</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1365" height="768" data-id="466"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Use-a-hand-blender-to-break-down-the-crushed-bones-to-powder.webp" alt="Use a hand blender to break down the crushed bones to powder" class="wp-image-466" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Use-a-hand-blender-to-break-down-the-crushed-bones-to-powder.webp 1365w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Use-a-hand-blender-to-break-down-the-crushed-bones-to-powder-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Use-a-hand-blender-to-break-down-the-crushed-bones-to-powder-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Use-a-hand-blender-to-break-down-the-crushed-bones-to-powder-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Use-a-hand-blender-to-break-down-the-crushed-bones-to-powder-800x450.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1365px) 100vw, 1365px" /><figcaption>Use a hand blender to break down the crushed bones to powder</figcaption></figure>
<figcaption class="blocks-gallery-caption">Using Stone Tools as DIY Mortar and Pestle to crush dried bones into smaller fragments</figcaption></figure>



<p>You can even use a normal mortar and piston used for crushing spices to crush the bones. </p>



<h4>Bone Meal Application to Papaya Tree </h4>



<figure class="wp-container-156 wp-block-gallery-155 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-default is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="467"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Organic-Self-Seeded-Papaya-Tree-Loaded-With-Fruits-1024x576.webp" alt="Organic Self Seeded Papaya Tree Loaded With Fruits" class="wp-image-467" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Organic-Self-Seeded-Papaya-Tree-Loaded-With-Fruits-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Organic-Self-Seeded-Papaya-Tree-Loaded-With-Fruits-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Organic-Self-Seeded-Papaya-Tree-Loaded-With-Fruits-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Organic-Self-Seeded-Papaya-Tree-Loaded-With-Fruits-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Organic-Self-Seeded-Papaya-Tree-Loaded-With-Fruits.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Organic Self Seeded Papaya Tree Loaded With Fruits</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="469"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-trench-around-the-papaya-tree-1024x576.webp" alt="Dig a trench around the papaya tree" class="wp-image-469" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-trench-around-the-papaya-tree-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-trench-around-the-papaya-tree-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-trench-around-the-papaya-tree-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-trench-around-the-papaya-tree-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-trench-around-the-papaya-tree.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Dig a trench around the papaya tree</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="470"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Add-2-3-Table-spoons-of-bone-meal-inside-the-trench-in-the-root-zone-1024x576.webp" alt="Add 2-3 Table spoons of bone meal inside the trench in the root zone" class="wp-image-470" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Add-2-3-Table-spoons-of-bone-meal-inside-the-trench-in-the-root-zone-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Add-2-3-Table-spoons-of-bone-meal-inside-the-trench-in-the-root-zone-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Add-2-3-Table-spoons-of-bone-meal-inside-the-trench-in-the-root-zone-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Add-2-3-Table-spoons-of-bone-meal-inside-the-trench-in-the-root-zone-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Add-2-3-Table-spoons-of-bone-meal-inside-the-trench-in-the-root-zone.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Add 2 to 3 Tablespoons of the bone meal inside the trench in the rooting zone</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="468"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-Cover-the-trench-With-Soil-and-Water-it-to-start-the-decomposition-process-1024x576.webp" alt="Cover the trench With Soil and Water it to start the decomposition process" class="wp-image-468" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-Cover-the-trench-With-Soil-and-Water-it-to-start-the-decomposition-process-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-Cover-the-trench-With-Soil-and-Water-it-to-start-the-decomposition-process-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-Cover-the-trench-With-Soil-and-Water-it-to-start-the-decomposition-process-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-Cover-the-trench-With-Soil-and-Water-it-to-start-the-decomposition-process-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/5-Cover-the-trench-With-Soil-and-Water-it-to-start-the-decomposition-process.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Cover the trench With Soil and Water to start the decomposition process</figcaption></figure>
<figcaption class="blocks-gallery-caption">Applying Bone Meal to my self seeded organic papaya tree</figcaption></figure>



<p>The bone meal requires soil microbes to decompose it makes the phosphorous and calcium plant available. So you need to apply it by digging a trench around the rooting zone. Apply 2-3 tablespoons for a large tree in the ground. After adding bonemeal cover the trench with soil and water it thoroughly to start the decomposition process.</p>



<h4>Bone Meal Application to Desert Rose <br></h4>



<figure class="wp-container-158 wp-block-gallery-157 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-2 is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="472"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Desert-Rose-Plant-in-Full-Bloom-1024x576.webp" alt="Desert Rose Plant in Full Bloom" class="wp-image-472" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Desert-Rose-Plant-in-Full-Bloom-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Desert-Rose-Plant-in-Full-Bloom-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Desert-Rose-Plant-in-Full-Bloom-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Desert-Rose-Plant-in-Full-Bloom-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Desert-Rose-Plant-in-Full-Bloom.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Desert Rose Plant in Full Bloom</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="473"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-Small-Hole-near-the-rooting-Zone-and-Apply-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-1024x576.webp" alt="Dig a Small Hole near the rooting Zone and Apply 1 Tablespoon of Bone Meal" class="wp-image-473" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-Small-Hole-near-the-rooting-Zone-and-Apply-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-Small-Hole-near-the-rooting-Zone-and-Apply-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-Small-Hole-near-the-rooting-Zone-and-Apply-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-Small-Hole-near-the-rooting-Zone-and-Apply-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-Small-Hole-near-the-rooting-Zone-and-Apply-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Dig a Small Hole near the rooting Zone and Apply 1 Tablespoon of Bone Meal</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="471"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-Soil-and-water-it-1024x576.webp" alt="Cover it up with Soil and water it" class="wp-image-471" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-Soil-and-water-it-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-Soil-and-water-it-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-Soil-and-water-it-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-Soil-and-water-it-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-Soil-and-water-it.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Cover it up with Soil and water it</figcaption></figure>
<figcaption class="blocks-gallery-caption">Increase flower blooms by applying bone meal to flowering plants</figcaption></figure>



<p>For potted plants, you can dig a small hole near the stem of the plant and apply 1 tablespoon of bonemeal. After adding bonemeal cover the hole with soil and water it thoroughly.</p>



<h4>Bone Meal Application to Yellow Trumpetbush</h4>



<figure class="wp-container-160 wp-block-gallery-159 wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-2 is-cropped">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="475"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Yellow-Trumpetbush-Plant-Grown-from-Cutting-with-Multiple-Blooms-1024x576.webp" alt="1 Yellow Trumpetbush Plant Grown from Cutting with Multiple Blooms" class="wp-image-475" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Yellow-Trumpetbush-Plant-Grown-from-Cutting-with-Multiple-Blooms-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Yellow-Trumpetbush-Plant-Grown-from-Cutting-with-Multiple-Blooms-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Yellow-Trumpetbush-Plant-Grown-from-Cutting-with-Multiple-Blooms-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Yellow-Trumpetbush-Plant-Grown-from-Cutting-with-Multiple-Blooms-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/1-Yellow-Trumpetbush-Plant-Grown-from-Cutting-with-Multiple-Blooms.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Yellow Trumpetbush Plant Grown from Cutting with Multiple Blooms</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="474"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-hole-in-the-rooting-zone-and-add-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-1024x576.webp" alt="2 Dig a hole in the rooting zone and add 1 Tablespoon of Bone Meal" class="wp-image-474" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-hole-in-the-rooting-zone-and-add-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-hole-in-the-rooting-zone-and-add-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-hole-in-the-rooting-zone-and-add-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-hole-in-the-rooting-zone-and-add-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal-800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/2-Dig-a-hole-in-the-rooting-zone-and-add-1-Tablespoon-of-Bone-Meal.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Dig a hole in the rooting zone and add 1 Tablespoon of Bone Meal</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="576" data-id="476"  src="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-soil-and-add-water--1024x576.webp" alt="3 Cover it up with soil and add water" class="wp-image-476" srcset="https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-soil-and-add-water--1024x576.webp 1024w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-soil-and-add-water--300x169.webp 300w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-soil-and-add-water--768x432.webp 768w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-soil-and-add-water--800x450.webp 800w, https://plantsmylove.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/3-Cover-it-up-with-soil-and-add-water-.webp 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Cover it up with soil and add water</figcaption></figure>
</figure>



<p></p>



<p>I hope friends, you liked this post about bone meal fertilizer and how to create and apply it to your garden. If yes, don’t forget to share this video with your friends and family whom you think could benefit from it. If you liked this, you might also like our other gardening-related content. Make sure to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/PlantsMyLove?sub_confirmation=1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">subscribe&nbsp;</a>to our YouTube channel or join our mailing list to be alerted as soon as a new video is released. Thanks for watching friends see you later bye.</p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/bone-meal/">What is Bone Meal? Benefits Making Application</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://plantsmylove.com/">Plants My Love</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
